Guide to the Map Collection, NYU Abu Dhabi Library AD.MC.019
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Map Collection, NYU Abu Dhabi Library
1561-2003
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
AD.MC.019
347 Leaves in 2 boxes and 8 flat file drawers.
Scope and contents
The Map Collection of the NYU Abu Dhabi Library was begun in 2014, following the establishment of the Archives and Special Collections department in library of the university's newly-opened Saadiyat Campus. As such, the collection was designed to be one of five core areas of Special Collections in the library, with an emphasis on preserving and making accessible rare or unique maps depicting the Arabian Peninsula, the Arabian Gulf, surrounding areas of the Middle East and the Indian Ocean rim.
One key area of early collecting has been that of maps from European cartographers, demonstrating the evolving understanding of the region from the 16th through the early 19th centuries. Driven by expanded commerce with South and East Asia during these centuries, and a corresponding need for more accurate maps and charts of the regions that merchants passed through, the collection contains examples of maps that range from late Renaissance era maps largely based on Ptolemaic understandings of the region, including fanciful names of non-existant towns, rivers, or mountain ranges; to those that demonstrate the innovations of 17th century Dutch and French cartography, which provided an increasingly accurate view of the contours of the Arabian Peninsula and surrounding regions, culminating in British works of the early 19th century, the product of a more active British commercial and military presence in the Gulf during that time.
Maps from the 20th century reflect a shift in commercial and military activities in the wider region, showing the impact of two World Wars, as well as the advent of the exploration and extraction of petroleum from countries around the Gulf and the Arabian Peninsula. Maps from the British-led Egyptian Expeditionary Forces that pushed the armies of Ottoman Turkey out of the Levant during World War I, hydrographic charts from the British Royal Navy, as well as maps from German and British forces during World War II, show that while the region was not central to the struggles of the European powers, it was not far from their minds.
With the exploitation of the region's petroleum resources, questions of the demarcation of boundaries became essential, and some maps, such as the U.S. Geological Survey maps of Saudi Arabia from the 1970s, sought to provide a more accurate depiction of previously uncharted parts of the region. As as new states were formed around the Gulf during the mid-to-late 20th century, as well as the rapid development of other countries in the region, maps began to depict the burgeoning national consciousness of countries such as Bahrain or the United Arab Emirates.
Most of the maps in this collection were acquired individually or as groups. However, other relevant maps exist in the Archives and Special Collections department, usually as component parts of archival collections (such as the J.B. Kelly or Chris Kutschera collections), or as component parts of cataloged books or atlases from the Special Collections.
Arrangement
Most of the maps in this inventory have been cataloged, and have corresponding bibliographic records in the library catalog of New York University. This finding aid was created to enable easier access to the contents of the collection as a whole, and to aid the browsability of the collection.
While most of the maps are physically arranged in storage by library classification numbers (Library of Congress classification numbers), or grouped together by their size, the arrangement used in this inventory groups the maps by geographic regions, and then within those categories, alphabetically by the names of the map creators. While the map title, creator, date of creation, publication information, and dimensions are recorded here, further information about individual maps may be found in the corresponding bibliographic records in the NYU Libraries catalog.
- Africa, 1855-1856
  - Colton, J. H. (Joseph Hutchins). Africa: North Eastern sheet, 1856; 1 Leaves 40 x 47 cm. (Box Maps B, Folder 8)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Publication data: New York, NY: J.H. Colton and Co.
    Library call number: G8220 .J43 1856
  - Colton, J. H. (Joseph Hutchins). Africa: North Western sheet, 1855; 1 Leaves 40 x 47 cm. (Box Maps B, Folder 10)
    Library call number: G8735 .J43 1855
- Arabian (Persian) Gulf, 1939-1993
  Scope and Contents
  Includes nautical charts of the Gulf, as well as maps of countries on the Arabian littoral of the Gulf (maps pertaining to Iran are included within the "Persia/Iran" series).
  - Bahrain. Dāʼirat al-Ashghāl al-ʻĀmmah. Bahrain Islands, 1968 (Map-case D, Drawer 1)
    Publication data: [Manama?] Public Works Dept., Bahrain Government
    Library call number: G7590 1968 .B3
  - Bandar Abbas, 1945; 1 Leaves
    Publication data: London: Edward Stanford Ltd
  - Brownbook Publishing. The great outdoors [cartographic material] (Map-case D, Drawer 1)
    Publication data: [Dubai]: Brownbook Publishing
    Library call number: G3201 .E65 B7 2010
  - Edgell, J.A. Persian Gulf: Um al-Qaiwain to Ras al Matbakh., 1939; 1 Leaves
    Publication data: [S.l.]: British Admiralty
  - Great Britain. Directorate of Military Survey. Bahrain 1:50,000 (2 parts: Bahrain North and Bahrain South), 1973 (Map-case D, Drawer 1)
    Publication data: [London]: Ministry of Defense
    Library call number: G7590 1973
  - Iraq-Kuwait Boundary Demarcation Commission. Takhṭīṭ al-ḥudūd al-dawlīyah bayna Jumhūrīyat al-ʻIrāq wa-Dawlat al-Kuwayt, 1993 (Map-case D, Drawer 5)
    Publication data: Kuwait: al-Umam al-Muttaḥidah, al-Lajnah
    Library call number: G7611.F2 1993 .I7
  - Southern, R.N. Persian Gulf, Trucial Oman. Ras Abu al Mishut to Fasht al Arif, 1947; 1 Leaves
    Publication data: [S.l.]: British Admiralty, 1947
    General
    4305234
  - United Kingdom. Admiralty. Hydrographic Office. [Collection of 34 UK Admiralty Charts: The Arabian Gulf]., 1950; 34 Leaves
    Publication data: London: United Kingdom. Admiralty. Hydrographic Office
- Arabian Peninsula, 1561-1977
  - Cheesman, R. E. (Robert Ernest). Arabia: routes between ʻOqair and Jabrin oasis in Eastern Nejd, 1925; 1 Leaves measuring 51 x 48 cm. (Map-case C, Drawer 1A)
    Publication data: London: Royal Geographical Society
    Library call number: G7521.S12 1925 .C4
  - Gastaldi, Giacomo [after Ptolemy]. Arabia Felice Nuova Tavola, 1561; 1 Leaves 22 x 28 cm. (Box Maps A, Folder 3)
    Publication data: Venetia: Appresso Vincenzo Valgrisi
    Library call number: G 7420 .P8 1561
  - Hole, William. Great Desert of Arabia, 1614; 1 Leaves 32 x 38 cm. (Box Maps B, Folder 5)
    Publication data: S.l.: s.n.
    Library call number: G7610 .H6 1614
  - Holt, A. L. Surveys of Syrian and Arabian Deserts, 1920-1922. The topography along the southern route has been amplified by H. St. J.B. Phillby..., 1925; 1 Leaves
    Publication data: London: War Office. General Staff. Geographical Section,
    Bibliographic number:
    7945553
  - Lallkan, P.G. (India. Army. Aden Troop). Map of country round Aden Arabia, 1872; 1 Leaves (Box Maps B, Folder 3)
    Publication data: Aden: Aden Troop Office
    Library call number: G7520 .L35 1872
  - Mariette, Pierre. Carte des trois Arabies: tirée en partie de l'Arabe de Nubie, en partie de divers autres autheurs., 1654; 1 Leaves
    Publication data: [s.l.]: Chez Pierre Mariette
  - Ottoman Military Engineers. Yemen Vilâyeti haritasi... / [The Ottoman Vilayet of Yemen.]., 1907; 1 Leaves
    Publication data: [S.l.]: [s.n.]
    7556533
  - Playfair, James. Arabia: drawn and engraved for Dr. Playfair's atlas, 1821; 1 Leaves
    Publication data: Edinburgh: Macredie Skelly and Co
  - US Geological Survey of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia (Darb Zubaydah Quadrangle), 1960 (Map-case D, Drawer 3)
  - US Geological Survey of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia (Wadi Al Batin Quadrangle), 1977 (Map-case D, Drawer 3)
  - US Geological Survey of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia (Northeastern Hijaz Quadrangle), 1977 (Map-case D, Drawer 3)
  - US Geological Survey of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia (Wadi Ar Rimah Quadrangle), 1977 (Map-case D, Drawer 3)
  - US Geological Survey of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia (Western Arabian Gulf Quadrangle), 1977 (Map-case D, Drawer 3)
  - US Geological Survey of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia (Central Arabian Gulf Quadrangle), 1977 (Map-case D, Drawer 3)
  - US Geological Survey of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia (Southern Najd Quadrangle), 1977 (Map-case D, Drawer 3)
  - US Geological Survey of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia (Northwestern Rubʻ al-Khālī Quadrangle), 1977 (Map-case D, Drawer 3)
  - US Geological Survey of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia (Eastern Rubʻ al-Khālī Quadrangle), 1977 (Map-case D, Drawer 3)
- Indian Ocean rim, 1598-1956
  - Asie Méridionale comprenant La Prequ'Il de L'Inde, La Perse, L'Afghanistan et le Beloutchistan, 1861; 1 Leaves
    Publication data: Paris: E. Andriveau-Goujon
  - Bartholomew, John, editor. Thacker's reduced survey map of India, 1925; 1 Leaves
    Publication data: Calcutta, Thacker, Spink and Co.
  - Bry, Johann Theodor de. Ailhae Cidade de Goa Metropolitana da Indiæ partes Orientais que esta en 15 Graos da Banda do Norte., 1601; 1 Leaves 39.5 x 43.5 cm. (Box Maps B, Folder 9)
    Publication data: [Francofurti]: [M. Beckerus]
    Library call number: G2283.G6 1601 B79
  - Castel Branco, José Frederico de Assa. Carta do Territorio portuguez de Goa, 1878; 1 Leaves
  - Ceylon Survey Office. City of Colombo and surroundings, 1956; 1 Leaves 106 x 64 cm.
    Publication data: Colombo: Survey Department
  - Janssonius, Jan / Ortelius, Abraham. Erythtaei Sive Rubri Maris Periplus, 1624 [?]; 1 Leaves (Map-case C, Drawer 1B)
    Publication data: Amstelodami [Amsterdam]
    Library call number: G9180 .O7 1624
  - Lattré, Jean. Carte du sisteme des courants des mers de l'Inde dans le tems de la mousson du N.E au N. de la ligne publiée par le chevalier Grenier en, 1776; 1 Leaves (Map-case C, Drawer 1B)
    Publication data: [Paris]: Le Vicomte Gremier
    Library call number: G9180 1776 .C3
  - Lattré, Jean. Carte des Courants pour le Tems de la Mousson du Indian Ocean au N. de la ligne, 1776
    Publication data: [Paris]: [Le Vicomte Gremier]
    Library call number: G9180 1776 .C37
  - Linschoten, Jan Huygen van. Deciniantur in Hac Tabula, Orae Maritimae Abexiae, Freti Mecani, 1598; 1 Leaves 39 x 52 cm. (Box Maps B, Folder 4)
    Publication data: London: Iohn Wolfe
    Library call number: G7520 .L556 1598
    4221531
  - Madras, 1922; 1 Leaves
    Publication data: London: Edward Stanford, Ltd
    7653943
  - Wit, Frederick de. Tabula Indiae Orientalis, 1662 (?); 1 Leaves measured as 50 x 62 cm. (Map-case C, Drawer 1B)
    Publication data: [Tot Amsterdam]: [Bij Frederick de Wit in de Calverstraet bij den Dam inde Witte Paskaert]
    Library call number: G8000 .W5 1662
- Middle East, general, 1593-1918
  - Bradford, T. G. (Thomas Gamaliel), 1802-1887. Persia, Arabia, Tartary, Afghanistan, 1835; 1 Leaves 23 x 30 cm. (Box Maps A, Folder 2)
    Publication data: [Boston: William D. Ticknor, 1835]
    Library call number: G 7420 .B73 1835
  - Colton, J. H. (Joseph Hutchins). Colton's Palestine, 1855; 1 Leaves 39 x 47 cm. (Box Maps B, Folder 2)
    Publication data: New York: J.H. Colton and Co.
    Library call number: G7500 .C7 1855
  - Jode, Cornelis de / Gastaldi, Giacomo. Secunda Partis Asiae, 1593 (Map-case C, Drawer 1A)
    Publication data:: [Antwerp]: [Arnold Coninx]
    Library call number: G7520 .G3 1593
  - L'Isle, Guillaume de. Carte de la Turquie, de l'Arabie et de la Perse, 1701; 1 Leaves measuring 49 x 65 inches. (Map-case C, Drawer 1A)
    Publication data: a Paris: Chez l'Auteur, Rue des Cannettes
    Library call number: G7420 .L5 1701
  - Egyptian Expeditionary Force. Map of Damascus., 1918; 1 Leaves (Map-case D, Drawer 5)
    Publication data: [S.l.]: [s.n.],
  - Egyptian Expeditionary Force. Syria / Haifa., 1918; 1 Leaves (Map-case D, Drawer 5)
    Publication data:
    [S.l.]: [s.n.]
  - Egyptian Expeditionary Force. Syria / Jerusalem., 1917; 1 Leaves (Map-case D, Drawer 5)
  - Ottens, R. (Reinier). Regnum Persicum Imperium Turcicum in Asia Russorum Provinciae ad Mare Caspium, circa 1723 (Map-case D, Drawer 1)
    Publication data: Amsterdam: Reinerus et Josua Ottens
    Library call number: G7420 .R2 1730
  - Speed, John. The Turkish Empire., 1626; 1 Leaves measuring xxxx (Map-case C, Drawer 1A)
    Publication data: [London]: Are to be sold in Popshead Alley by G. Humble
    Library call number: G7400 .S64 1626
  - Stopendael, Daniel; Keur, Pieter; and Keur, Jacob. De Gelegentheyt van't Paradys ende t'Landt Canaan, mitsgaders de eerst bewoonde Landen der Patriarchen, uyt de H. Schristure en verscheyden auctoren by een gestdlt., 1702; 1 Leaves 39 x 47 cm. (Box Maps B, Folder 1)
    Publication data: Netherlands: [s.n]
    Library call number: G7481.2 .S7 1702
  - Wit, Frederik de. Nova Persiae Armenia Natoliae et Arabiae, 1686?; 1 Leaves measuring 52 x 61 inches. (Map-case C, Drawer 1A)
    Publication data: T'Amsterdam: By Frederick de Wit in de Kalversbraet in de Witte Pascaert
    Library call number: G7420 .W5 1666
- Persia / Iran, 1613-1974
  - Anville, Jean Baptiste Bourguignon d'. Carte de l'Empire de Perse, 1779; 1 Leaves measuring 50 x 62 cm. (Map-case C, Drawer 1A)
    Publication data: Venice: P. Santini
    Library call number: G7620 .A5 1779
  - Blaeu, Willem Janszoon. Persia Sive Sophorum Regnum, 1634; 1 Leaves 45 x 60 cm. (Box Maps B, Folder 6)
    Publication data: [Amsterdam]: Guiljelmus Blaeu
    Library call number: G7620 .B5 1634
  - Delisle de Sales, Jean-Baptiste-Claude, 1739?-1816. Carte de l'Ancienne Perse, Divisée en XX. Satrapies, 1782; 1 Leaves 25 x 43 cm. (Box Maps A, Folder 5)
    Publication data: Paris: [s.n.]
    Library call number: G 7621 .S3 .D45 1782
  - Mercator, Gerard. Persici Vel Sophorum Regni Typus, 1613; 1 Leaves 44 x 53 cm. (Box Maps B, Folder 7)
    Publication data: [Amsterdam]: [Jodocus Hondius]
    Library call number: G7621 .S25 .M4 1613
  - Muʼassasah-i Jughrāfiyāʼī va Kārtūgrāfī-i Saḥāb. Guide map of Bushehr, 1974; 1 Leaves (Map-case C, Drawer 1B)
    Publication data: Tehran: Sahab Geographic and Drafting Institute
    Library call number: G7624.B9 1974 .M8
  - Seutter, Matthaeus. Opulentissimi Regni Persiae juxta suas provincias recentissima, 1740?; 1 Leaves measuring 54 x 62 cm. (Map-case C, Drawer 1B)
    Publication data: [Augsburg]: [Matthaei Seutteri]
    Library call number: G7620 .S8 1740
  - Speed, John. The Kingdom of Persia: With the chief cities and habities described, 1626; 1 Leaves (Map-case C, Drawer 1A)
    Publication data: London: G. Humble
    Library call number: G7620 .S7 1676
- Red Sea, 1740-1817
  - Bellin, Jacques Nicolas, 1703-1772. Carte de la Coste d'Arabie, Mer Rouge, 1740; 1 Leaves 25 x 37 cm. (Box Maps A, Folder 4)
    Publication data: Paris, France: Bellin [excerpted from La Harpe, Jean-François de. Histoire générale des voyages.]
    Library call number: G 7520 .B4 1740
  - Thomson, John. Arabia, Egypt, Abyssinia, Red Sea &c., 1817; 1 Leaves measuring 54 x 71 cm. (Map-case C, Drawer 1A)
    Publication data: Edinburgh: J. and G. Menzies
    Library call number: G7520 .T5 1817
- Tübingen Atlas des Vorderen Orients (TAVO) = Atlas of the Near and Middle East., 1994-2003
  Publication data: Wiesbaden: L. Reichert; Berlin: Distributed by Kai-Henning Gerlach
  Library call number: F2205 .T8
  - Portfolio vol. 1. Section A I maps 1-7. Relief, hydrology and settlement., 1994 (Map-case C, Drawer 2A)
  - Portfolio vol. 1. Section A II maps 1-6. Geology., 1994 (Map-case C, Drawer 2A)
  - Portfolio vol. 1. Section A III maps 2-6. Geomorphology., 1994 (Map-case C, Drawer 2A)
  - Portfolio vol. 1. Section A IV maps 1-6. Middle East Climate., 1994 (Map-case C, Drawer 2A)
  - Portfolio vol. 1. Section A V maps 1-4. Hydrogeography, 1994 (Map-case C, Drawer 2A)
  - Portfolio vol. 1. Section A VI maps 1-8. Vegetation, 1994 (Map-case C, Drawer 2A)
  - Portfolio vol. 2. Section A V maps 9-16. Vegetation / Fauna, 1994 (Map-case C, Drawer 2A)
  - Portfolio vol. 2. Section A VII maps 1-2, 4. Natural regions., 1994 (Map-case C, Drawer 2A)
  - Portfolio vol. 2. Section A VIII maps 1-18. Population, 1994 (Map-case C, Folder 2A)
  - Portfolio vol. 3. Section A IX maps 1-10. Settlement., 1994 (Map-case C, Drawer 2B)
  - Portfolio vol. 3. Section A X maps 1-13, 15-20. Economy and communication, 1994 (Map-case C, Drawer 2B)
  - Portfolio vol. 4. Section B I maps 1-9, 11-18. History, Stone Age., 1994 (Map-case C, Drawer 2B)
  - Portfolio vol. 4. Section B II maps 1-15. History, early and middle Bronze Age, 1994 (Map-case C, Drawer 2B)
  - Portfolio vol. 5. Section B III maps 1-8. Second half of the 2nd Millennium B.C., 1994 (Map-case C, Drawer 2B)
  - Portfolio vol. 5. Section B IV maps 1-23. The 1st Millennium B.C. down to the Age of Alexander the Great., 1995 (Map-case C, Drawer 2C)
  - Portfolio vol. 5. Section B V maps 1-9, 11-13. Hellenism and the Roman Periods, 1995 (Map-case C, Drawer 2C)
  - Portfolio vol. 6. Section B V maps 15-19, 21-22. Hellenism and the Roman Periods., 1996 (Map-case C, Drawer 2C)
  - Portfolio vol. 6. Section B VI maps 1-8, 10-12, 14-18. Late antiquity., 1997 (Map-case C, Drawer 2C)
  - Portfolio vol. 6. Section B VII maps 1-10, 12-14, 16-19. The expansion of Islam up to the time of the First Crusade (1096), 1998 (Map-case C, Drawer 2C)
  - Portfolio vol. 7. Section B VIII maps 1-2, 4-8, 10, 12-20. From the crusader period up to 1510., 2000 (Map-case C, Drawer 2C)
  - Portfolio vol. 7. Section B IX maps 1-13, 15, 18,-19, 21-25. The Ottoman period up to 1918., 2001-2003 (Map-case C, Drawer 2D)
- Other, 1719-1937
  - Anville, Jean Baptiste Bourguignon d'. Premiere Partie de la Carte d'Asie, 1751 (Map-case D, Drawer 1)
    Publication data: a Paris: Chez l'Auteur aux Galleries du Louvre
    Library call number: G7420 .A5 1751
  - Bradford, T. G. (Thomas Gamaliel), 1802-1887. Eastern Hemisphere, 1835; 1 Leaves 23 x 29 cm. (Box Maps A, Folder 1)
    Publication data: [Boston: W.D. Ticknor, 1835]
    Library call number: G 6570 .B73 1835
  - Chatelain, Henri Abraham. Carte des Indes, de la Chine & des Iles de Sumatra, Java &c., 1719; 1 Leaves measured as 53 x 61 cm. (Map-case C, Drawer 1B)
    Publication data: [Amsterdam: Chez L'Honore et Chatelain Libraires
    Library call number: G8000 .C47 1719
  - Colton, J. H. (Joseph Hutchins). Colton's Australia, 1856; 1 Leaves 39 x 47 cm. (Box Maps B, Folder 11)
    Library call number: G8950 .C7 1856
  - Delamarche, Charles François. Afrique: divisée en ses principaux empires et royaumes, 1795; 1 Leaves 55 x 71 cm. (Map-case C, Drawer 1B)
    Publication data: Paris: Chez Delamarche
    Library call number: G8200 .D4 1795
  - Lizars, Daniel. Asia: [in two panels], circa 1820 (Map-case D, Drawer 1)
    Publication data: Edinburgh: Daniel Lizars
    Library call number: G7400 .L5 1820
  - Petermann, August. Russisch-turkisch-persisch-englische Grenzländer von Bosnien bis Kaschgar und Indien, 1877; 1 Leaves 56 x 69.5 cm.
    Publication data: Gotha: Justus Pethes
  - Stanford's Commercial Map of Asia., 1937
    Publication data: London: E. Stanford